In building the foundations for
cognition, researchers have endowed AI
neurons with the capacity for Pavlovian
learning. Plants also may well be
sentient, but if we consider plants
sentient, we might also have to consider
the capacity for AI to be sentient,
especially with much of the research
that's coming out now. This is a hotly
contested field, and I'm starting to
think that humans just don't know what
they're doing. Either way, we'll talk
about it. You may remember this paper
from 2016, in which a group of
researchers demonstrated that plants
could associate a neutral stimulus, so a
fan blowing on them, with light. They
would grow towards that fan even in the
absence of light. This led to one of my
favorite things in science, where people
publish letters, which are essentially
just commentary in journals about each
other's research. Yes, somebody said
that they could not replicate it,
therefore there was not sufficient
evidence for sentience in plants, and
they responded again saying they didn't
set up the research properly when they
tried to replicate it. Science gets
really messy, and I have fun with that.
Now, I should note that there is no
unified way to test sentience. Sentience
is a capacity to have an experience.
Some researchers believe that all life
is sentient because all life responds to
stimuli, negative and positive, and
others want to attach additional
criteria, like associative learning. So,
think Pavlov's dog. You ring a bell, and
then you start salivating because you're
expecting candy. Also important to note
that we have seen associative learning
in plants long before people have been
arguing about a fan. Yes, mimosa plants
will stop scrunching up their leaves if
you keep on touching them because they
know they're not going to get eaten. I
say, "No." This also could be considered
habituation, so they just keep getting
hit by the same again and again, so they
just stop responding. Animals that don't
even have a brain are capable of
learning. We know some jellyfish are
capable of learning a map by looking at
the trees above the water. How do they
do that? Well, essentially, their entire
body operates like a brain, even though
they don't have a traditional brain like
we do. Animals like sea anemones, too,
technically don't have a brain, but they
are nicer to other anemones that are
related to them. We don't know how they
know they are related to them, either.
And of course, same with plants. It's
also been demonstrated that plants will
move their leaves to give plants that
are related to them more sunlight. Still
don't know how they know.
But back to synthetic neurons and maybe
one day synthetic brains. This research
group made synthetic neurons that are
capable of associative learning, which
is considered to be a major step towards
cognition. That's what our neurons can
do. They have to react on an individual
basis and then communicate with each
other. So when you think of associative
learning, think of Pavlov. You ring a
bell and then you get a treat. So when
you ring the bell, you start salivating
immediately. There's kind of a similar
thing that you can do with hardware,
apparently.
They used memristors, which is a
combination of transistor and memory.
They can remember the voltage that
passes through it and remain physically
changed as a result. These synthetic
neurons will fire if they get a
significant amount of voltage. So they
paired a weak voltage that should not
have caused a neuron to fire with a
strong one and they started associating
the strong with the weak, so they fired
with the weak voltage. This is not
magic. These are synthetic neurons that
have been trained and remain physically
changed as a result of that training.
This is actually really important
because this is something our neurons
can do individually. And together, they
make a whole that we consider to be
conscious. This could be the foundation
of cognition for neuromorphic hardware,
which is of course something that I
really like. I don't think we'll ever
reach sentience or consciousness from an
LLM. It's just a probability matrix just
spinning out what is most likely. But if
we can create something that has
intelligence that is ingrained to a
synthetic system, so it doesn't have a
computer that's working with zeros and
ones, it is the set of synthetic neurons
that are creating cognition. I think
that is how we'll get to sentience. And
it seems we're really darn close.
However, given that we continue to
argue, we don't know what an experience
is like from a plant. We barely know
what an experience is like in us. We can
only know our own internal world.
I seriously doubt that many would even
accept any kind of an experience coming
from something synthetic. Even if it
acted exactly like a person, even if we
modeled the human brain perfectly in
silicon, which by the way is very likely
to be carbon-based and I'm excited for
it that I just don't think people could
accept it because they can't imagine
what it's like in that world, even if
robots ask for rights. Not everyone
would be down with it. I'm not even sure
what I'm expecting. Now, the research is
really cool and as always when the
robots rebel, I'll probably be the one
to tell you about it and I'm on their
side, fellow humans.